Guide to the Pach Brothers Portrait Photograph Collection 1867-1947, undated (bulk 1880s-1940s) PR 84
New-York Historical Society
Pach Brothers Portrait Photograph Collection
1867-1947, undated (bulk 1880-1940)
New-York Historical Society
PR 84
4.86 Linear feet (9 boxes)
Portrait collection including photographs of nationally prominent people and socially prominent New Yorkers.
Provenance
The bulk of the collection was received in two separate gift from Philip M. Plant (733 photographs, November 22, 1937) and the Pach Brothers firm (339 photographs, July 28, 1947). Oscar White, the last owner of the studio, dontaed an additional four prints. Portraits of Harry Truman and Lyndon Johnson, taken by Mr. White, as well as a photograph of Pach's Photograph Gallery in New Jersey and a photo of a Pach photographer wagon were added in 2007.
Access Restrictions
Materials in this collection may be stored offsite. For more information on making arrangements to consult them, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Biographical Note
The Pach Brothers photographic firm was in business in New York City for over a century and a quarter. In that time, the location of its main portrait studio, following fashionable New Yorkers, migrated uptown from its start on the Bowery in the mid-1860s to upper Fifth Avenue in the mid-1960s, before closing its doors in the East 50s in the mid-1990s. Patrons included famous and ordinary Americans involved in business, politics, government, medicine, law, education, and the arts, as well as thousands of students, families and children who sat for Pach cameras from 1866 onward. Despite a devastating fire in 1895, which destroyed their New York studio and processing rooms as well as their entire negative archive, the Pach Brothers firm continued photographing for another hundred years with a second generation of Pach men behind the lens.
The original Pach Brothers photographers in New York City were Gustavus (1848-1904), Gotthelf (1852-1925), and Morris (1837-?). Born in Berlin, Germany, they came to New York as babies, and began their photographic career as boys. According to their newspaper obituaries, the brothers became intrigued with the new science of photography in the mid-1860s, and traveled the streets of their New York neighborhood taking pictures of local residents. Gustavus Pach made his first appearance in the 1866-1867 New York City directory where he and Morris were listed individually as photographers working at 260 Bowery, with an additional entry for "Pach Brothers" at the same address. Morris Pach alone remained in the directory the next year with no occupation listed. Gustavus Pach's obituary provides an explanation for his own disappearance from the directory: respiratory problems resulted in his leaving for Toms River, New Jersey.
The summer of 1868 found the Pach brothers in Long Branch, New Jersey, a shore town that was a favorite resort for wealthy Philadelphians such as George W. Childs and Anthony J. Drexel. There the brothers had the opportunity to make portraits of the families of Childs, Drexel and their close friend Ulysses S. Grant, who, in turn, were impressed with the brothers' photographic work and ambition. Grant, Childs, and Drexel pooled funds to underwrite the Pach brothers' first photographic studio there, which was built at Long Branch on the grounds of the United States Hotel, as well as their mobile horse-drawn darkroom.
While Morris Pach stayed in New Jersey working as a cigar maker, Gustavus Pach returned to New York in time to be listed in the 1871-1872 city directory in a studio at 858 Broadway. He changed addresses twice before settling in at 841 Broadway in 1877, where he remained in business through 1890. In the 1881-1882 directory, a listing appears for the first time for G.W. Pach & Brothers; the next year the brothers are also individually listed. A fourth Pach brother, Oscar (1850-1903) was the business manager for the firm; he immigrated to the United States in 1873 and worked with his brothers until his death. A full listing of Pach Brothers studios in New York follows this biographical note. A series of chronologically arranged pictures of the buildings that housed the Pach studios are filed in Series III. In each of those photographs, the Pach business is represented to varying degrees: a 1905 image of the 935 Broadway address is really a fine, dramatic portrait of the iconic Flatiron Building, to the left of which can be seen a relatively tiny Pach Brothers trade sign.
In addition, from the 1870s Pach Brothers operated studios (perhaps just seasonally) in college towns, where they specialized in photographing generations of athletes and student groups at Princeton, Yale, Harvard, Columbia, Vassar, and West Point; all processing and finishing work was done in New York. The firm also did record photography for the Metropolitan Museum of Art and, for many years, documented paintings, sculptures, and other artworks in that collection. Pach Brothers exhibited their photographs at international expositions including the 1876 Centennial Exposition in Philadelphia, the 1884 World's Industrial and Cotton Centennial Exposition in New Orleans, and the 1893 World's Columbian Exposition in Chicago. They also had work accepted at the annual exhibitions held by the American Institute of the City of New York, and the Photographers Association of America.
The Pach brothers themselves appear to have lived and photographed concurrently in New York City and various towns in New Jersey throughout their lives. The 1880 United States Census described the entire Pach family living together in Ocean, Monmouth County, New Jersey: father J. M. Pach (age 68), mother Johanna (age 66), and their four sons Barney (a baker, age 34), Augustus W. (photographer, 32), Oscar (photographer, 30), and Godfrey (photographer, 28), and one daughter Bertha (at home, 31). Morris Pach (cigar maker, 43) was listed separately living in Shrewsbury, Monmouth County, with his wife and five children.
A dramatic fire on February 16, 1895 completely burned out the Pach studios that were located on the top floor of the buildings at 935 and 937 Broadway. An account in the New York Timess (February 17, 1895, p. 17) stated that there were thirty employees at work in the studio, and twenty patrons sitting for their portraits, when the fire started in the negative retouching room. No lives were lost, though all negatives created in the New York and the college satellite studios from the time of the firm's founding were destroyed. The brothers immediately reconstructed their premises and continued photographing from that same location for more than fifteen years.
A second generation of Pach photographers joined the studio in 1898 when Morris's son Alexander L. Pach (1863-1938) took up the camera. Deaf from childhood, Alexander worked with the firm for most of his life. One of Gotthelf's two sons, Alfred (1884-1965), became involved with the family business in 1903, and was its president at the time of his death. His other son, Walter (1883-1958), was a respected painter, printmaker, and art critic, though, according to city directories, he worked at the Pach studio from 1909 to 1914 as an "artist" (possibly a colorist). Several other non-family members became associated with the firm after 1914. Oscar White was the president of the Pach Brothers corporation when it closed in 1994; he had worked for the company since 1939.
Gustavus Pach retired from the New York studio in 1903 and bought out the New Jersey studios (including Lakewood and Long Branch) of Pach Brothers; he died the next year. Oscar Pach became an invalid in 1902 and died the following spring. Gotthelf Pach retired from the firm in 1919 and died in New York in 1925 after several years of failing health. Studio portraits of the Pach brothers and family members associated with the firm can be found in Box 6, folder 50.
Philip M. Plant, who donated the first group of Pach Brothers photographs to The New-York Historical Society, was described in his New York Times obituary as a "sportsman, gentleman farmer and millionaire playboy." The adopted son of Colonel Morton F. Plant, a Connecticut railroad and steamship magnate who was one of the earliest developers of Florida's west coast, Philip Plant resided in New York and bred pheasants at his Waterford, Connecticut, estate. He was a benefactor of the American Museum of Natural History, and president of the Ornamental Pheasant Society. Married three times, Plant died in New York on June 15, 1941, at the age of 40. A Pach Brothers portrait of Plant ran accompanied his obituary in the New York Times.
Pach Brothers New York City Studio Addresses (as listed in New York city directories, business directories and telephone books)
1866-1867 260 Bowery (Gustavus and Morris Pach as "Pach Brothers")
[1868-1871 absent from city directories]
1871-1877 858 Broadway (Gustavus W. alone)
1877-1881 841 Broadway (Gustavus W. alone)
1881-1885 841 Broadway (Gustavus, Gotthelf & Oscar as "G.W. Pach & Brothers")
1885-1890 841 Broadway (Gustavus, Gotthelf & Oscar as "Pach Brothers")
1890-1902 935 Broadway ("Pach Brothers" listed hereafter)
1902-1903 935 Broadway and 571 Fifth Avenue
1903-1913 935 Broadway
1913-1914 925 Broadway and 570 Fifth Avenue
1914-1933 570 Fifth Avenue
1933-1939 642 Fifth Avenue
1939-1956 5 East 57th Street
1956-1967 673 Fifth Avenue
1967-1994 16 East 53rd Street
Scope and Content Note
The Pach Brothers Portrait Photograph Collection contains over 1000 photographs produced by that New York commercial portrait studio between its founding in the mid-nineteenth century and 1947. The collection is entirely photographic, and holds no negatives, correspondence files, patron cards, or business and financial records. It contains only selected examples of Pach Brothers work, and is by no means meant to be a comprehensive archive of this prolific firm's vast output.
The portrait collection was assembled by Pach Brothers and came to The New-York Historical Society in two separate gifts. Approximately two-thirds of the photographs were donated by Philip M. Plant, who purchased for the Society a group of images that Pach Brothers had arranged and displayed as the exhibition "American Personalities Through Seven Decades" at their New York studio in October 1937. The firm added more portraits to the collection before Plant presented it to the Historical Society one month later. A decade after, Pach Brothers endeavored to bring the Society's holdings up to date by donating a group of "portraits of famous Americans, 1940-1947" with the specific intent of their being added to "the Pach Collection." Each photograph is stamped on the verso with an accession date (a November 22, 1937, date for the Plant gift, and July 28, 1947, date for the Pach Brothers addition), making it possible to determine the provenance of each image.
With very few exceptions, the photographs in the collection are not specifically dated though considering style, sitter life dates, and the firm's devastating 1895 fire, most of the portraits can be ascribed to the first third of the twentieth century. Prints that came in as the 1947 Pach gift will date from 1940 to 1947. Copyright dates do occasionally appear on the photographs: for example, Winfield Scott Schley's portrait is dated 1888, Mrs. Charles Evans Hughes' portrait is marked 1906, and the photograph of President McKinley with his cabinet was copyrighted in 1901.
The Pach Brothers Portrait Photograph Collection is arranged in three series: Individual and Family Portraits; Oversize and Group Portraits; and Buildings.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in three series:
Missing Title
Series I. Individual and Family Portraits
Series II. Oversize and Group Portraits
Series III. Buildings
Related Material at the Department of Prints, Photographs, and Architectural Collections
Additional Pach Brothers portrait photographs appear throughout the New-York Historical Society Library's collections, particularly in the Department of Prints, Photographs and Architectural Collections' Portrait File (PR 052) and Theatrical Portrait File (PR 104), as well as in many family photograph collections. At least two examples of Pach Brothers work can be found in the Carte de Visite Photograph File (PR 011). There are more than thirty Pach Brothers images of New York City and New Jersey in the Stereograph File (PR 065).
The Museum of the City of New York holds 75,000 Pach negatives that they acquired in 1995. The Monmouth County Historical Association in Freehold, New Jersey has a smaller collection of several hundred negatives from the New Jersey studios.
Actors -- United States -- Portraits.; Actresses -- United States -- Portraits.; Businessmen -- United States -- Portraits.; Inventors -- United States -- Portraits.; Motion picture actors and actresses -- United States -- Portraits.; Politicians -- New York (State) -- Portraits; Portrait photography -- New York (State) -- New York.; Presidents -- United States -- Portraits; Upper class -- United States -- Portraits.; Portraits.; Studio portraits; Portrait photographers; Group portraits.; Morgan, J. Pierpont (John Pierpont), 1837-1913 -- Portraits; New York Giants (Baseball team) -- Pictorial works; Pickford, Mary, 1892-1979 -- Portraits; Riis, Jacob A. (Jacob August), 1849-1914; Roosevelt family -- Portraits; Ross, Harold Wallace, 1892-1951 -- Portraits; Russell, Lillian, 1861-1922 -- Portraits; Seton, Ernest Thompson, 1860-1946 -- Portraits; Sickles, Daniel Edgar, 1825-1914 -- Portraits; Skinner, Otis, 1858-1942 -- Portraits; Sloan family -- Portraits; Talmadge, Constance, 1898-1973 -- Portraits; Talmadge, Norma, 1897-1957 -- Portraits; Tiffany, Louis Comfort, 1848-1933 -- Portraits; Twain, Mark, 1835-1910; Vail, Theodore Newton, 1845-1920 -- Portraits; Vanderbilt family -- Portraits; Villard, Oswald Garrison, 1872-1949 -- Portraits; Washington, Booker T., 1856-1915 -- Portraits; Webb, Clifton, 1893-1966 -- Portraits; Willkie, Wendell L. (Wendell Lewis), 1892-1944 -- Portraits; Zukor, Adolph, 1873-1976 -- Portraits; Adams, Maude, 1872-1953 -- Portraits.; Arliss, George, 1868-1946; Astor family; Barrymore, Ethel, 1879-1959 -- Portraits; Belasco, David, 1853-1931 -- Portraits; Belmont, August, 1813-1890 -- Portraits; Berlin, Irving, 1888-1989. -- Portraits; Bryan, William Jennings, 1860-1925 -- Portraits; Carnegie, Andrew, 1835-1919 -- Portraits; Cassini, Igor, 1915-2002 -- Portraits; Cerf, Bennett, 1898-1971 -- Portraits; Chaplin, Charlie, 1889-1977 -- Portraits.; Comstock, Anthony, 1844-1915; Dempsey, Jack, 1895-1983 -- Portraits; Eastman, George, 1854-1932; Edison, Thomas A. (Thomas Alva), 1847-1931; Fairbanks, Douglas, 1883-1939 -- Portraits; Folger, Henry Clay, 1857-1930 -- Portraits; Gibson, Charles Dana, 1867-1944 -- Portraits; Gilbert, Cass, 1859-1934 -- Portraits; Gilder, Richard Watson, 1844-1909 -- Portraits; Goelet (Family) -- Portraits; Guggenheim family -- Portraits; Hammerstein, Oscar, II, 1895-1960 -- Portraits; Harlow, Jean, 1911-1937; Havemeyer (Family) -- Portraits; Hearst, William Randolph, 1863-1951 -- Portraits; Hitchcock, Raymond, 1865-1929 -- Portraits; Jefferson, Joseph, 1829-1905; Knopf, Alfred A, 1892-1984 -- Portraits; Lawrence, Gertrude -- Portraits; Lewis, Sinclair, 1885-1951; Lillie, Beatrice, 1894-1989 -- Portraits; Mansfield, Richard, 1857-1907 -- Portraits; Marconi, Guglielmo, 1874-1937; May, Edna, 1878-1948 -- Portraits; Mellon, Andrew W. (Andrew William), 1855-1937 -- Portraits; Morgan, Helen, 1900-1941 -- Portraits; Morgan, J. P. (John Pierpont), 1867-1943 -- Portraits
- Series I: Individual and Family Portraits
  Scope and Contents note
  Series I. Individual and Family Portraits holds images of men and women, some with family members, photographed primarily in one of the Pach Brothers studios. The sitters are nearly all Americans, and are a mix of nationally prominent personalities and socially prominent New Yorkers. The portraits are predominantly 10 x 8 inch black and white photographs affixed to 12 x 8.5 inch tan one-ply boards on which the patron's name and life dates have been typed below the image. A second format in the collection is what Pach Brothers, in their 1947 gift, described as "Large-Size Portraits," or unmounted 12 x 9 inch gelatin silver prints.
  In addition, there are random pre-1900 albumen prints present in various sizes and formats. Several sepia-toned albumen group portraits of Ulysses Grant and George W. Childs with their family and friends were taken at their Long Branch, New Jersey, homes in the 1870s. Other individual portraits, such those of as Frederick Barnard (who was provost of Columbia University from 1864 to 1884 and died in 1889), Luke Blackburn, and William Henry Crane were certainly made in the early 1880s. Many of the albumen prints are in a 3.5 x 2.75 inch oval format mounted on the same labeled tan boards (Antoinette Carter Hughes is one example) described above. There are also a few photographs mounted on Pach's standard commercially-produced printed cabinet card boards, such as the portraits of United States Attorney General Henry Wise, banker Giovanni Morosini and his daughter Giulia, and the noted Lilliputian boxer Ebert P. Zink. There is one example of a nineteenth-century Pach Brothers stereograph in the collection, a portrait of Nellie Grant Sartoris, the popular daughter of President Grant.
  The collection also includes copy prints, showing that the Pach studios also turned out second-generation images at the request of their patrons. Photographs include a group portrait of Rutherford Hayes's presidential cabinet made from a print, portraits of Admiral David Farragut and James Garfield, and a photograph of an engraved portrait of Abraham Lincoln. There are two photographs of George Dewey, one a nineteenth-century albumen print and one a later silver gelatin print made from the same negative. Two other photographs have format notes of interest to show Pach Brothers techniques. Explorer Robert E. Peary's portrait has an arc of light through the right side of the image revealing that it was printed from broken glass negative, and a group portrait of the Stokes family includes thirty two family members, some of whom were added to the photograph by the composite technique. Most of the photographs are not signed, but many (for instance, Seth Low) have the Pach name blind stamped in the lower right corner of the image.
  The photographs in this collection were nearly all taken in one of the Pach Brothers studios, and are generally head-and-shoulders portraits of seated patrons. However, the verso of Ebert Zink's cabinet card portrait carries a printed advertisement for the firm that states their willingness to photograph "At your own Home when necessary," and a few portraits made at other sites can be found. For example, Ethel Barrymore was photographed in bed cradling her first child, and Madam Nijinski posed in front of a fireplace over which hung photographs of dancer Vaselev Nijinski. David Belasco, Andrew Carnegie, Virginia Gildersleeve, Luigi Palma di Cesnola, and Walter Lippman were photographed at their office desks, Charles Addison Miller in his office, and Mark Twain in his writing studio. Off-site occupation-related images are here as well: Thomas Lipton stood shipboard on a catwalk. William Crane Carl, in his robes, played a large pipe organ in his portrait, lyricist Leo Ditrichstein sat at the keyboard of a grand piano for his, and the duo Van & Schenk posed with two grand pianos. Artist Robert Henri stood holding paintbrushes with an unfinished portrait on his easel and sculptor John Quincy Adams Ward posed with a maquette. Illustrator Otto Soglow sat a drawing board working on a sketch of his famous character "The Little King," and Ham Fisher posed casually with one of his cartoons. Thomas Edison was photographed twice, including one portrait made in his laboratory office beside a cylinder-recording machine.
  Political figures include every American president from Ulysses S. Grant through Franklin D. Roosevelt as well as several New York State governors and New York City mayors. There are a just few portraits of foreign officials, including Heinrich Bruning, chancellor of Germany, French diplomat Compte de Paris, Persian Consul General Haigazoun H. Topakyan, and Wu ting-Fang, Envoy Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary of China to the United States. Theatre and film personalities are present, such as Maude Adams, Charles Chaplin, Douglas Fairbanks, Joseph Jefferson, Jean Harlow, Richard Mansfield (represented by three portraits, two of which are in costume) and Edna May. Literary and cultural figures include Sinclair Lewis, Richard Watson Gilder, Oscar Hammerstein, Irving Ramsey Wiles, Bennett Cerf, and Igor Cassini (known as Cholly Knickerbocker) among others.
  The majority of the Pach Brothers' portraits are straightforward and formal in style and, though distinguished, somewhat unremarkable. There are occasional instances of overt glamour. Catherine Calvert was draped in furs and jewels, and Frieda Hempel, swathed in diamonds, posed with her little dog. Gertrude Lawrence chose pearls and feathers to accessorize her portrait, and Rita Weiman donned very stylish drop earrings laden with pearls. Raymond Hitchcock was dapper in his striped trousers, bowler hat and silver-handled cane. The Pach portraitists were, however, certainly capable of producing artistic work as demonstrated by perhaps the most dramatic and arresting image in the collection: a pensive portrait of actress Julia Marlowe. She was lit from above to accentuate the ethereal mass of her upswept hair and splendid fur-edged cape, and to reflect just the right light back into her upturned eyes.
  However, most of the Pach patrons found in this collection are American businessmen, with a smattering of men of religion, military officers, jurists, and cultural figures; they are largely shown attired in suits, daywear, or evening clothes. Prominent New York families are well represented, and the collection includes portraits of Astor, Goelet, Guggenheim, Havemeyer, Roosevelt, Sloan, and Vanderbilt men among others.
  The Pach Brothers Portrait Photograph Collection holds a single image for each sitter unless indicated by a number in parentheses following a name in the box and folder list. Some patrons returned to sit for the Pach Brothers over the years: Edward Finch had three separate portraits taken throughout his career, and Virginia Gildersleeve was photographed at two stages of her administrative career, both times at the same desk in the same office. Charles Evans Hughes' second portrait was taken much later in his life when his hair and beard had turned white. Portraits of children or youths in the collection are few, and are of sitters who made repeat visits to the Pach studios. J. Schuyler Casey was photographed three times, once at age one and again as a student at Mount Pleasant Academy. John J. Pershing has four portraits, two made while he was a cadet at the United States Military Academy at West Point (from which he graduated in 1886) and two taken later in his military career. Theodore Roosevelt is pictured six times over the course of his life, the last time posed holding his grandson.
  The photographs in the Pach Brothers Portrait Photograph Collection are filed alphabetically by sitter surname. Names are listed in accordance with established Library of Congress name authority records, and cross references have been added to any which have been moved when the collection was processed (for instance, Samuel Clemens is now filed under Twain, and Dorothy Dix is filed as Elizabeth Gilmer). Oversize images are filed in Box 9, with cross-references in the Series I box list.
  There is a single portrait of each each sitter unless a number follows after the name.